Guide to the National Education Association-Special Collections records, 1857-2015 NEA1007.RG
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
- Affiliates, 1967-1977; Series 9; 4.5 Linear Feet
  - Western Regional Leadership Conference, Portland, OR, February 6 1980 - February 24 1980; series 9 (Box 4502, Folder 21)
  - West Virginia Classroom Teachers Association Thirteeth Annual Spring Conference Banquet, April 9, 1949; Series 9 (Box 4933, Folder 1)
  - Wisconsin Education Association Council: A History, 2001; series 9 (Box 4310, Folder 8)
  - Wisconsin Education Association- Steve Jobs, 1996; Series 9 (Box 4623, Folder 22)
  - What the Executive Secretary Expects of the Magazine, June 25, 1959; Series 9 (Box 4721, Folder 15)
  - What's Left After The Right? A Resource Manual For Educators, April 1990; Series 9 (Box 4911, Folder 12)
  - Workbook for New State Staff Orientation, Washington D.C., 2003 November 13-15; Series 9 (Box 4657, Folder 3)
- National Education Association Retirees Organization, 2014; Series 10; 0.5 Linear Feet
  In 1971, the NEASO went on strike and ended up changing the culture of the 1971. In addition to regular salary increases, the staff received guarantees of grievance arbitration and more vacation time. Retired N.E.A. staff, however, did not receive any benefits. In a July, 1971 report to the NEA retirees, Dick Kennan, director of the Professional Rights and Responsibilities unit, noted "Few people are still at NEA who sacrificed to build the organization, who worked for very low salaries and who went on half-pay for many months: so we elders have little voice to win interest in fair treatment." In November 8, 1971, the first NEARO meeting was held. Attendees included Sam Lambert, Don Morrison, Dale Robinson, John Starie, Lyle Ashby, Elizabeth Berckman, Charles Bish, Ivan Booker, Lee Boyer, Helen Campbell, Poppy Christian, Lois Clark (Michigan), Bertha Cornell, Louise Crown, Eva Cummins, Edwin Davis, Agnes Dalboe, Hazel Davis, Howard Dawson, Thelma Dietz, Robert Eaves, Lucille Ellison, Wilda Faust (Florida), Elizabeth Geib, Ernest Giddings, Laura Heintel and Frank Hubbard. It was only in 1985 that NEARO successfully won a cost of living adjustment for its members. In 1989, an automatic, annual pension increase was promised. These and other gains came from the work of the many volunteers who have taken an active role in the organization over the years. The list of presidents over the years includes: Ivan Booker, Charles Bish, Lois Rogers, Merrill Hartshorn, Margaret Stevenson, Sylvia Brotman, T. Marcus Gillespie, Anna Hyer, Dave Darland, Alice Cummings, Marty Ware, Byron Spice, Norma Plater, Dick Mallory, Bill Dresser, Dorothy Massie and current president Hazel Blakey.
  Series contains one newsletter donated by members of NEARO.
  - Annual Dinner Honoring Retirees of the NEA, 1994-1995; series 10 (Box 4379, Folder 5)
  - Fifteenth Annual Dinner Honoring Retirees of the National Education Association, 2002 September 20; Series 10 (Box 4992, Folder 3)
  - NEA Retired, 1994 May; Series 10 (Box 4992, Folder 4)
  - NEA Retired, 1994 July; Series 10 (Box 4992, Folder 5)
  - NEA Retired, 1994 November; Series 10 (Box 4992, Folder 6)
  - NEA Retired, 1995 May; Series 10 (Box 4992, Folder 7)
  - NEA Retired, 1995 July; Series 10 (Box 4992, Folder 8)
  - NEA Retired, 1996 January; Series 10 (Box 4992, Folder 9)
  - NEA Retired, 1996 March; Series 10 (Box 4992, Folder 10)
  - NEA Retired, 1998 January; Series 10 (Box 4992, Folder 11)
  - NEA Retired, 1998 March; Series 10 (Box 4992, Folder 12)
  - NEA Retired, 1998 May; Series 10 (Box 4993, Folder 1)
  - NEA Retired, 1998 July; Series 10 (Box 4993, Folder 2)
  - NEA Retired, 1998 September; Series 10 (Box 4993, Folder 3)
  - NEA Retired, 1998 November; Series 10 (Box 4993, Folder 4)
  - NEA Retired, 1999 January; Series 10 (Box 4993, Folder 5)
  - NEA Retired, 1999 March; Series 10 (Box 4993, Folder 6)
  - NEA Retired, 1999 May; Series 10 (Box 4993, Folder 7)
  - NEA Retired, 1999 July; Series 10 (Box 4993, Folder 8)
  - Outreach [Newsletter], 2014; Series 10 (Box 4008, Folder 21)
  - Outreach [Newsletter], 2015; Series 10 (Box 4040, Folder 15)
  - Sixteenth Annual Dinner Honoring Retirees of the National Education Association, 2003 September 12; Series 10 (Box 4993, Folder 9)
  - This Active Life: 6 Ways to Thrive in Retirement, 2003 September; Series 10 (Box 4993, Folder 10)
  - This Active Life: A Helping Hand, 2000 May; Series 10 (Box 4993, Folder 11)
  - This Active Life: A Place to Call Home, 2004 March; Series 10 (Box 4994, Folder 1)
  - This Active Life: A Teacher for Life, 2000 November; Series 10 (Box 4994, Folder 2)
  - This Active Life: All in the Family, 2008 March; Series 10 (Box 4994, Folder 3)
  - This Active Life: Any Questions?, 2007 May; Series 10 (Box 4994, Folder 4)
  - This Active Life: Avoiding the Trap, 2005 September; Series 10 (Box 4994, Folder 5)
  - This Active Life: Bad Medicine, 2004 January; Series 10 (Box 4994, Folder 6)
  - This Active Life: Blazing New Trails, 2000 September; Series 10 (Box 4994, Folder 7)
  - This Active Life: Can't Get Enough, 2006 November; Series 10 (Box 4994, Folder 8)
  - This Active Life: Decision Time, 2004 September; Series 10 (Box 4994, Folder 9)
  - This Active Life: Extreme Travel, 2006 January; Series 10 (Box 4994, Folder 10)
  - This Active Life: Family Ties, 2009 September; Series 10 (Box 4994, Folder 11)
  - This Active Life: Fighting Fires, 2001 July; Series 10 (Box 4994, Folder 12)
  - This Active Life: Fighting for Fair Drug Prices, 2003 January; Series 10 (Box 4995, Folder 1)
  - This Active Life: First Rites, 2005 January; Series 10 (Box 4995, Folder 2)
  - This Active Life: Following Her Dream, 2002 January; Series 10 (Box 4995, Folder 3)
  - This Active Life: Going Global, 2003 November; Series 10 (Box 4995, Folder 4)
  - This Active Life: Growing Great Teachers, 2009 November; Series 10 (Box 4995, Folder 5)
  - This Active Life: History Lessons, 2008 January; Series 10 (Box 4995, Folder 6)
  - This Active Life: Is This the Nursing Home of the Future?, 2006 May; Series 10 (Box 4995, Folder 7)
  - This Active Life: Mentoring a New Generation, 2002 November; Series 10 (Box 4995, Folder 8)
  - This Active Life: Money Matters, 2009 January; Series 10 (Box 4995, Folder 9)
  - This Active Life: Preserving an Island Paradise, 1999 November; Series 10 (Box 4995, Folder 10)
  - This Active Life: Preserving the Past in Pewter, 2002 May; Series 10 (Box 4995, Folder 11)
  - This Active Life: Reading to Succeed, 2000 July; Series 10 (Box 4995, Folder 12)
  - This Active Life: Reclaiming Hope, 2003 March; Series 10 (Box 4996, Folder 1)
  - This Active Life: Retirees to the Rescue, 2006 September; Series 10 (Box 4996, Folder 2)
  - This Active Life: Retirees to the Rescue, 2007 September; Series 10 (Box 4996, Folder 3)
  - This Active Life: Running to Save Lives, 2001 March; Series 10 (Box 4996, Folder 4)
  - This Active Life: School Days, Redux, 2009 March; Series 10 (Box 4996, Folder 5)
  - This Active Life: Second Wind, 2006 March; Series 10 (Box 4996, Folder 6)
  - This Active Life: Soaring to New Heights, 2000 January; Series 10 (Box 4996, Folder 7)
  - This Active Life: Soul of a Woodworker, 2001 September; Series 10 (Box 4996, Folder 8)
  - This Active Life: Speak Up! Speak Out!, 2008 September; Series 10 (Box 4996, Folder 9)
  - This Active Life: Stay On Your Toes, 2007 November; Series 10 (Box 4996, Folder 10)
  - This Active Life: Staying on Top, 2001 November; Series 10 (Box 4996, Folder 11)
  - This Active Life: Still Practicing After All These Years, 2000 March; Series 10 (Box 4996, Folder 12)
  - This Active Life: Taking Care, 2003 July; Series 10 (Box 4997, Folder 1)
  - This Active Life: Taking Time to Tutor, 2001 January; Series 10 (Box 4997, Folder 2)
  - This Active Life: The Art of the Story, 2002 March; Series 10 (Box 4997, Folder 3)
  - This Active Life: The Bonus Years, 2004 May; Series 10 (Box 4997, Folder 4)
  - This Active Life: The Face of Alzheimer's, 2005 November; Series 10 (Box 4997, Folder 5)
  - This Active Life: The Healing Power of Holding, 1999 September; Series 10 (Box 4997, Folder 6)
  - This Active Life: The Money Crunch, 2002 September; Series 10 (Box 4997, Folder 7)
  - This Active Life: The Power of Play, 2009 May; Series 10 (Box 4997, Folder 8)
  - This Active Life: The Retirement Chronicles, 2005 March; Series 10 (Box 4997, Folder 9)
  - This Active Life: The Technophiles, 2008 May; Series 10 (Box 4997, Folder 10)
  - This Active Life: The Trojan Horse of Pension 'Reform', 2005 May; Series 10 (Box 4997, Folder 11)
  - This Active Life: Watch Out!, 2003 May; Series 10 (Box 4997, Folder 12)
  - This Active Life: We Are NEA-Retired, 2008 November; Series 10 (Box 4998, Folder 1)
  - This Active Life: Words of Wisdom, 2007 March; Series 10 (Box 4998, Folder 2)
  - This Active Life: World Class, 2007 January; Series 10 (Box 4998, Folder 3)
  - This Active Life: Writing the Next Chapter, 2004 November; Series 10 (Box 4998, Folder 4)
- Public Relations Council of the States, 1990-2009; series 11
  The Series is arranged alphabetically by title, then chronologically by year.
  In the late 1960's, state association public relations staffers and member od the NEA Press, Radio and Television Relations Devision reached the same conclusion...it was time to bring PR directors together from around the country.
  State association editors had been meeting for several years, but until 1969, PR people had not been providede the opportunity to assemble as a group. A decision was reached to bring together those who listed public relations coordination as part of their job assignment.
  The site for the first gathering was New Orleans, Louisiana. Here on January 15-17, 1969, the Public Relations Council was born.
  Staff members from 44 states met at the Bourbon Orleans Hotel in the French Quarter. Theme of the meeting was "NEA - State Public Relations to Strengthen Locals."
  There was a diverse mix of staff in attendance: editors, business managers, public relations directors, and state convention coordinators. NEA paid the full travel cost for the participants.
  Following the conference, a summary booklet was printed which put the seminar issues into a public relations practitioner's resource phamplet: "What is the State Association PR job?"
  In 1970, the group reassembled in Ft. Lauderdale, Florida. The following year it was out west to Las Vega, Nevada.
  Since then, the PR Council has met annually, always in January.
  Source: "The Story of the PR Council 1969-1990" NEA Public Relations Council of the States, January, 1990
  The series contains records created or held by the P.R. Council of the States, including handbooks and historical materials.
  - 40 Years...A Look Back: A Family of Communicators Growing Together: The Story of the NEA PR Council of the States, ca. January 2009; series 11 (Box 4310, Folder 9)
  - 1997 PR Council Handbook, series 11 (Box 4310, Folder 10)
  - 2002 PR Council Handbook, series 11 (Box 4310, Folder 11)
  - The Complete Communications Catalogue: 1991 Edition: A Compendium of Resources Compiled by the NEA Public Relations Council of the States, series 11 (Box 4310, Folder 12)
  - National Standards [1 of 2], 2002; Series 3 (Box 4903, Folder 11)
  - National Standards [2 of 2], 2002; Series 11 (Box 4903, Folder 4)
  - The Story of the PR Council 1969-1990, January 1990; series 11 (Box 4310, Folder 13)
  - Wegmann Mayrose, 2004; Series (Box 4885, Folder 4)
- Oral Histories, 2017; Series 12; 8 item(s) 4 oral histories and 4 transcripts
  Immediate Source of Acquisition
  Digital recordings were made by Vakil Smallen between January 19th and May 5th, 2017. They were uploaded to the Internet Archive in Feberuary, 2018.
  Arranged alphabetically by surname of interviewee
  This series consists of digital recordings and transcriptions of interviews of retired NEA staff members conducted by Vakil Smallen, the archivist for the NEA collection.
  Labor unions -- United States -- History -- 20th century; Education policy; Melley, Ken; Dunlop, John; Lestina, Dale; Nuanes, Richard
  - Interview with John Dunlop, March 2, 2017; Series 12
    Biographical / Historical
    John Dunlop was elected president of the Birmingham Education Association (BEA) in 1967 and hired by the National Education Association (NEA) in 1970. He began his career at NEA by doing field work before he joined the Office of Negotiation. He worked directly with local NEA affiliates who were involved in negotiations, bargaining, and strikes.
    Link to audio recording
    https://archive.org/details/NEA1007RG_s12_Dunlop
    Link to transcript
    https://archive.org/details/NEA1007RG_s12_Dunlop_Transcript
  - Interview with Dale Lestina, May 5, 2017; Series 12
    Dale Lestina worked for the National Education Association (NEA) from 1968 through 1999, mostly with the Legislative Department. For most of his career, he was the NEA's Chief Lobbyist.
    https://archive.org/details/NEA1007RG_s12_Lestina
    https://archive.org/details/NEA1007RG_s12_Lestina_Transcript
  - Interview with Richard Nuanes, February 16, 2017; Series 12
    Richard Nuanes worked at the National Education Association from 1976 through 2010, splitting his time between Legal Services and Conference and Facilities Management.
    Link to audio recordings
    https://archive.org/details/NEA1007RG_s12_Nuanes
    https://archive.org/details/NEA1007RG_s12_Nuanes1_Transcript
  - Interview with Ken Melley, January 19, 2017; Series 12
    Ken Melley worked at the National Education Association (NEA) from 1968 through 1997. His career began as an organizer of teachers to support collective bargaining initiatives. In 1979, he became the Political Director of NEA. He was also the founder of the Uniserv program and oversaw the NEA's Political Action Committee (NEAPAC).
    https://archive.org/details/NEA1007RG_s12_Melley
    https://archive.org/details/NEA1007RG_s12_Melley_Transcript
- National Education Association Health Information Network, Series 13
  - AIDS Memorial Quilt: Draft Project Outline, 1992; Series 13 (Box 4971, Folder 7)
  - National Education Association Health Information Network Responding to HIV and AIDS, 1992; Series 13 (Box 4903, Folder 6)
  - National Education Association Health Information Network, 1992; Series 13 (Box 4911, Folder 13)
  - School Crisis Guide, Undated; Series 13 (Box 4683, Folder 6)